Welcome back to AM Northwest. Do you own a piece
of ivory? Maybe inherited a few from grandma?
Well, there are new laws about owning,
buying, and selling ivory here with a lowdown.
We welcome
back antique appraiser Gary Germer. Good to
see you again. These are kind of incredible.
I think
you know a lot of people do have probably
at least one piece that they inherited,
right? You do and
I get called a lot during you know that I am
liquidating estates or people they've inherited.
What do I do? It could be worth a lot. So you
have a piece like these at the end here that are
all Chinese. Well, this one's Japanese
carvings that are wonderful works of art.
They're just
beautiful works of art, but the laws have
changed in order to protect the elephants.
Oh, sure. So
what are the laws? Well, you got to understand
there's the fish and wildlife is who sets the
laws and there's the US fish and wildlife
and there's the state fish and wildlife.
So the US
fish and the wildlife about five or six years
ago, they were the state fish and wildlife.
So
now they're black Americans in China and They
had little attempts with paper sculpting really
five or six years ago made it to where they deal
with interstate and enter importing and stuff
like that. And so basically if it comes
to new elephant ivory, you can't use it.
It's you can't
buy it. It's the easiest appraisal I can do.
Okay. What's it worth? It's worth nothing because
you
can't sell it. So would these be worth nothing
then because you can't sell do you cannot sell
these pieces here that are here now? How
do you know that their new elephant ivory?
Well, you can
Well, you know you can tell that it's ivory or
maybe from trying to tight caught fish there
was their
one of the things is and i don't know if this
would show up on camera but you can see it here
where you see this like cross hatching oh right
and it's the way that the tooth grows is one
of
the ways you tell that it's ivory okay so um you
know there are exceptions we're going to talk
about but the bottom line is is that it's going
to be assumed that it's not sellable till you
can
prove otherwise and the exceptions would be one
would be age now these are too new they have
to
be at least 100 years old and so these are too
new okay the this here painting is done on ivory
i should just leave it there so the camera can
do i think you read a photographer's mind only
there
were a few other words in there okay that that's
done on a sheet of ivory that's it that that
paint
portraits were done and so we'd have to prove
that that artist and the stuff by the style of
her
clothes and stuff that
this was all done before um
18 or excuse me 1920 or 1919 okay and so that's
kind of on the borderline and so sometimes when
it comes to proving the age that it's over 100
years old yeah you need documentation family
lore is not enough my great grandfather brought
this in and can't say that well you you can
say
it's it's like trying to prove to the irs you
didn't earn any money you got to prove you didn't
okay and so they they make it a lot so it's
oftentimes like to hire a qualified appraiser
can sometimes be worth more than the
items worth but like i was just in new york
at the met and they had a whole room full of
15th century ivory carvings i mean those are
worth a fortune so it would be worth if you had
an heirloom
like that right to have the work done but for
most part stuff that guys brought back from world
war
ii or after world war ii or or you know merchant
marine stuff in the 20th century you can't
sell it
so now the exceptions are they found out first
of all they were going to try to make it to where
you
couldn't sell any ivory at all well then they
realized then you have a piano that's a hundred
thousand dollars worth of ivory and they're going
to try to make it to where you couldn't sell
any ivory at all well then they realized then
you have a piano that's a hundred thousand
dollars antique steinway you can't sell it so
what they made it the law is is you can sell it
if ivory
is a part of of the item like this has ivory
hands and face silver oftentimes says ivory here
and here
that have ivory and those are done as insulators
to keep the handle cool as you're as you're
using
it piano is another good example and that and
the piano is a good benchmark for you to remember
yeah you can have the item has to be
the ivory has to be part of the item
but has to be more less than 15 percent of the
volume of the item and 15 percent of the value
of
the item and it can't be over 200 grams and the
reason they use 200 grams that's about how much
ivory's in an 88 key piano oh okay so it's
about size of a cue ball right but tell me about
this
oh sorry go ahead so like this it looks like
it's all ivory but it's sliced so thin and this
dates to the 1880s and it's also sliced
so thin that it's less than 15 percent
and lastly tell me about this one this one here
is a walrus ivory now this is a whole different
subject walruses are not endangered but there
are laws pertaining to buying and selling it
when it comes to hunting the walruses you have
to be a native um alaska eskimo inuit native
you have to uh you cannot sell they can only
sell the raw ivory and we can handle it because
it's
been decorated by a native artist if
this had not had the scrimshaw on it
signed by a native artist but you couldn't sell
it but because you have if you have alaskan
ivory
that's decorated you can sell it all right gary
thank you all good information i appreciate
that